我在哈佛最难忘的回忆之一发生在1975年1月
one of my biggest memories of Harvard came in January 1975 when I made a call
那时我从宿舍给位于Albuquerque的一家公司打了一个电话，
from career house to a company in  Albuquerque new mexico that have begun
那家公司已经在着手制造世界上第一台个人电脑，
making the world's first personal  computer
我提出想向他们出售软件，我很担心他们会发觉我是一个住在宿舍的学生，
I offered to sell them software I worried they would realize I was just a
从而挂断电话，
student in a dorm and hang up on.
但是他们却说:“我们还没准备好，
instead they said we're not quite ready
一个月后你再来找我们吧。” 这是个好消息，
come see us in a month which was a good  thing,
因为那时我软件还根本没写出来呢。
because we hadn't written the software yet.
就是从那时起，我日以继夜地在这个小小的课外项目上工作，
from that moment I work day and night on the extra credit project that marked the
这导致了我学生生活的结束，以及通往微软公司的不平凡的旅程开始，
end of my college education and the  beginning of a remarkable journey with
不管怎样，我对哈佛的回忆主要都与充沛的精力和智力活动有关，
Microsoft what I remember above all about Harvard was being in the midst of
哈佛的生活令人愉快，也令人感到压力。
so much energy and intelligence
有时甚至会感到泄气，
it could be exhilarating intimidating  sometimes even discouraging
但永远充满了挑战性。
but always challenging
生活在哈佛是一种吸引人的特殊待遇，虽然我离开得比较早，
it was an amazing privilege and though I left early
但是我在这里的经历，在这里结识的朋友，在这里发展起来的一些想法，永远地改变了我。
I was transformed by my years at Harvard the friendships I made and the ideas I worked on.
但是，如果现在严肃地回忆起来，
but taking a serious look back,
我确实有一个真正的遗憾，我离开哈佛的时候，根本没有意识到
I do have one big regret I left Harvard with no real awareness of the awful
这个世界是多么的不平等，
inequities in the world
人类在健康、财富和机遇上的不平等大得可怕，
the appalling disparities of health and well an opportunity that condemn
它使得无数的人们被迫生活在绝望之中。
millions of people the lives of despair
我在哈佛学到了很多经济学
I learned a lot here at Harvard about new ideas and
和政治学的新思想
economics and politics
我也了解了很多科学上的新进展，
I got great exposure to the advances being made in the sciences
但是，人类最大的进步并不来自于这些发现，
but humanity's greatest advances are not in its discoveries but in how those
而是来自于那些有助于减少人类不平等的发现。
discoveries are applied to reduce inequity
鼓掌......
yeah
不管通过何种手段，民主制度、健全的公共教育体系，高质量的医疗保健，
whether through democracy strong public education quality health care are broad
还是广泛的经济机会， 减少不平等始终是人类最大的成就。
economic opportunity producing an equity is the highest human achievement
我离开校园的时候，根本不知道在这个国家里，有几百万的年轻人
I left campus knowing little about the  millions of young people cheated out of
无法获得接受教育的机会，我也不知道，
educational opportunities here in this  country and I knew nothing about the
发展中国家里有无数的人们生活在无法形容的贫穷和疾病之中。
millions of people living in unspeakable poverty and disease in developing countries
我花了几十年才明白了这些事情，在座的各位同学，你们是在与我不同的时代来到哈佛的
it took me decades to find out you graduates came to Harvard at a different time
你们比以前的学生更多地了解
you know more about the worlds in equities than the classes that came
世界是怎样的不平等，
before in your years here
在你们的哈佛求学过程中，我希望你们已经思考过一个问题，
I hope you had a chance to think about how in this age of accelerating
那就是在这个新技术加速发展的时代，我们怎样最终应对这种不平等，
technology we can finally take on these inequities and we can solve them
以及我们怎样来解决这个问题，为了讨论的方便，请想象假如你每个星期
imagine just for the sake of discussion that you had a few hours a week and a
可以捐献一些时间，每个月可以捐献一些钱，你希望这些时间和金钱可以用到对
few dollars a month to donate to a cause and you wanted to spend that time
拯救生命和改善人类生活有最大作用的地方，
and money or would have the greatest impact in saving and improving lives
你会选择什么地方？这也是我和Melinda（盖茨夫人）面临的问题。
where would you spend it？ for Melinda and I the  challenges the same
我们如何能将我们拥有的资源发挥出最大的作用，
how can we do the most good for the  greatest number with the resources we have
在讨论过程中，Melinda和我读到了一篇文章，里面说在那些贫穷的国家，
during our discussions on this question Linda and I read an article about the
每年有数百万的儿童死于
millions of children were dying every year in poor countries from diseases
在美国早已不成问题的疾病。
that we had long ago made harmless in  this country
麻疹、疟疾、肺炎、
measles malaria pneumonia
乙型肝炎、黄热病，还有一种以前我从未听说过的轮状病毒
hepatitis B yellow fever one disease that I had never heard of rotavirus was
每年导致50万儿童的死亡。
killing half a million children each year
但是在美国一例死亡病例也没有。我们被震惊了，
none of them in the United States we  were shot we'd assumed
我们想如果几百万儿童正在死亡线上挣扎，而且他们是可以被挽救的，
that millions of children were dying and they could be saved the world would make
那么世界理应将用药物拯救他们作为头等大事。
it a priority to discover and deliver  the medicines to save them.
但是事实并未如此，那些价格还不到一美元的救命药剂
but it did not for under a dollar
并没有送到他们的手中。
there were interventions that could save lives - just weren't being delivered
如果你相信每个生命都是平等的
if you believe that every life has equal value
那么我们无法接受某些生命被拯救了，而另一些生命 却被放弃了。
it's revolting to learn that some lives  are seen as worth saving and others are not
我们对自己说，事情不可能如此，但如果这是真的，
we said to ourselves this can't be true， but if it is true
那么它理应是我们努力的头等大事，所以我们开始行动，
it deserves to be the priority of our  giving. so we began up and begin our work
用任何人都想得到的方式开始工作。
in the same way anyone here would begin  it.
我们问：“这个世界怎么可以眼睁睁看着这些孩子死去？”
we asked how could the world let these  children die?
答案很简单，也很令人难堪。在市场经济中，拯救儿童是一项
by the answer is simple and harsh，the market did not reward
没有利润的工作，政府也不会提供补助。
saving the lives of these children, and  governments did not subsidize it.
这些儿童之所以会死亡，是因为他们的父母在经济上没有实力，
So the children died because their  mothers and fathers had no power in the
在政治上没有能力发出声音。但你们和我两者都具备，
market and no voice in the system. but  you and I have both.
我们可以让市场更好地为穷人服务，
we can make market for forces work better for the poor
如果我们能发展出一种更有创新性的资本主义制度，
if we can develop a more creative  capitalism
如果我们可以改变市场让更多的人可以获得利润，
if we can stretch the reach of market  forces so that
或至少能自食其力，这就可以帮到那些
more people can make a profit or at least earn a living
正在极端不平等的状况中受苦的人们。
serving people who are suffering from the great in equities
我们还可以向全世界的政府施压，要求他们将纳税人的钱
we can also press governments around the  world to spend taxpayer money in ways
花到更符合纳税人价值的地方，
that better reflect the values of the  people who pay the taxes if we can find
如果我们能够找到这样一种方法，既可以帮到穷人，又可以为商人带来利润，
approaches that meet the needs of the poor in ways that generate profits for
为政治家带来选票，
business and votes for politicians
我们就找到了一种减少世界性不平等的可持续的发展道路。
we will have found a sustainable way to reduce inequity in the world.
这个任务
now this task
是无限的，它不可能被完全完成，但任何自觉地解决这个问题的尝试，
is open-ended it can never be finished . But a conscious effort to answer this
都将会改变这个世界。
challenge can change the world.
在这个问题上，我是乐观的，但我也遇到过那些感到绝望的怀疑论者，
I'm optimistic that we can do this but I talked to skeptics claim there is no hope.